Guide to the W.H. Cowley Papers SC0196
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Personal papers and writings, Series 1
  - Correspondence, writings and speeches, 1922-1978; Series 1B
    - Correspondence with Hartree, Douglas, R., University of of Cambridge, concerning his concept of structure., 1957 Oct-Nov (Box 29, Folder 57-20)
    - WHC memo about procedures to students taking courses with him, 3 pages., 1957 Jun 28 and Sep 28 (Box 29, Folder 57-21)
    - Correspondence with Caplow, Professor Theodore H., about academic government and higher educational history., 1957 May-1958 Apr (Box 29, Folder 57-22)
    - Papers concerning the Conference on the Study of Higher Education, Palo Alto. See also 57-23A., 1957 Oct (Box 29, Folder 57-23)
    - Papers related to 57-23., 1957 (Box 29, Folder 57-23A)
    - J.B. and Hefferlin, Earline work reports., 1957 (Box 29, Folder 57-24)
    - "The American Academic Presidency," WHC memo written for Dodds, President H. W., of Princeton University, Stanford, 33 pages. See also 58-4 and 58-7., 1957 Dec 31 (Box 29, Folder 57-25)
    - Discussion papers related to Hefferlin, J.B. Lon, dissertation., 1957-1959 (Box 29, Folder 57-26)
    - Correspondence with Griffith, Coleman, about his taxonomic ideas and their bearing upon the Office of statistical Research and Information of the American Council on Education., 1957 Jul-Dec (Box 29, Folder 57-27)
    - INCORRECT NUMBER (Box 29, Folder 57-28)
    - Professional notes accession lists., 1957 (Box 29, Folder 57-29)
    - Correspondence with Pepperdine, Grace, Woods, J.M.’s secretary about JMW interviewing project., 1956 Jan-1957 Jun (Box 29, Folder 57-30)
    - Correspondence with Riesman, David, about student attitudes., 1956 Nov-1958 Jul (Box 29, Folder 57-31)
    - Student comments about WHC's teaching., 1957 (Box 29, Folder 57-32)
    - Correspondence with McGrath, Earl J. about higher educational history, the length of the Harvard course, and WHC's views on liberal education., 1956 Aug-1957 Jun (Box 29, Folder 57-33)
    - "The Diversity of American Life and the Development of Higher Education," text from panel discussion, Values and Higher Education, at the Stanford Conference on Higher Education, 11 pages., 1958 Mar 26-29 (Box 29, Folder 58-1A)
    - "The Distinctive Characteristics of American Higher Education," excerpt from WHC article, "The Higher Learning Versus the Higher Education," for Values and Higher Education panel of the Stanford Conference on Higher Education., 1958 Mar (Box 29, Folder 58-1B)
    - "The Administration of Colleges and Universities," text for panel discussion, Values and Higher Education, of the Stanford Conference on Higher Education, Appendix F, 12 pages. See also 57-13 and 58-21., 1958 Mar (Box 29, Folder 58-1C)
    - Correspondence associated with 58-1 A-C. (Box 29, Folder 58-1D)
    - "College and University Teaching, WHC article, Educational Record, pages 311-326., 1858-1958 (Box 29, Folder 58-2)
    - "College and University Teaching, 1858-1958," WHC article, The Two Ends of the Log, edited by Cooper, Russel M.. Includes related correspondence. See also 58-2., 1858-1959 (Box 29, Folder 58-2A)
    - WHC letter to Murray, Sister Gerard Maria about Catholicism and American Freedom, 3 pages., 1958 May 8 (Box 30, Folder 58-3)
    - WHC memo to Dodds, President H.W. About his study of the academic presidency, 39 pages. See also 57-25, 58-4A, 58-7., 1958 Jun 10 (Box 30, Folder 58-4)
    - Correspondence with Dodds, Harold W. and others about Dodds' book on the academic presidency., 1957 Jun-1962 May (Box 30, Folder 58-4A)
    - "Diverse Educational Paths," WHC memo written for Gardner, John W., of the Carnegie Corporation. 61 pages. Also contains related correspondence., 1958 Jun-1959 Jun (Box 30, Folder 58-5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence with McGrath, Earl J. about his research on liberal education., 1958 Apr-1960 Jan (Box 30, Folder 58-6)
    - "A Tentative Outline with Some Text of a Book on the History of the Academic Presidency," WHC study for President Dodds, 96 pages., 1958 Aug 30 (Box 30, Folder 58-7)
    - Correspondence with Pullias, Professor E.V., of USC about WHC's higher educational program at Stanford., 1957 Sep-1958 Feb (Box 30, Folder 58-8)
    - "The Liberal Arts College in the 20th Century," outline of WHC address at the All-College Lecture of the University of California at Santa Barbara. Folder includes news clippings., 1958 Oct 14 (Box 30, Folder 58-9)
    - Papers and correspondence related to WHC's semester teaching at the University of Illinois, and discussion with Henry, President Dave about teaching there permanently., 1958 Oct-1960 Jan (Box 30, Folder 58-10)
    - "Three Brief Discussions of the Humanities," WHC memo written for Rhinelander, Dean Philip. 14 pages., 1958 Sep 26 (Box 30, Folder 58-11)
    - WHC memo about the Stanford University School of Education (SUSE) higher education program for the Asilomar Conference and the self-study committee, 6 pages., 1958 Nov 1 (Box 31, Folder 58-12A)
    - WHC memo to the Co-ordinating Committee of the SUSE self-study committee, 4 pages., 1958 Nov 17 (Box 31, Folder 58-12B)
    - Correspondence with Spaght, M.E., of the Shell Companies Foundation and others about WHC’s historical writings., 1958 Nov-1959 Jan (Box 31, Folder 58-13)
    - Correspondence with Martorana, S.V., of the U.S. Office of Education about WHC's writings on the history of the junior college., 1957 Oct-1958 Jul (Box 31, Folder 58-14)
    - Correspondence with Kirkpatrick, Paul, about his paper "On Colleagues and Clients.", 1958 Oct-1961 Mar (Box 31, Folder 58-15)
    - Professional notes accession sheets., 1958 (Box 31, Folder 58-16)
    - Correspondence with the University of Chicago Press about their contract with WHC to publish his Professors, Presidents, and Trustees. Book was published after WHC's death by Jossey-Bass Inc., 1958 Jul-1967 May (Box 31, Folder 58-17)
    - Correspondence with U.S. Office of Education officials about defining higher educational terminology., 1958 Apr-1959 Sep (Box 31, Folder 58-18)
    - Writings of the "Quilp Quidnunc," a Cowley family newsletter. Folder contains only an excerpt from the 10/12/58 issue., 1958 Oct 12 (Box 31, Folder 58-19)
    - "The Traits of Face-to-Face Leaders," WHC's Ph.D. dissertation included in The study of Leadership, edited by Browne, C.C. and Cohn, Thomas S, Interstate Printers and Publishers, Inc. pages 227-234. See also 31-1., 1958 (Box 31, Folder 58-20)
    - "Administration of American Colleges and Universities," WHC address, Kansai University Bulletin. 12 pages. Includes correspondence., 1957-1959 (Box 31, Folder 58-21)
    - Letters from students commenting on WHC courses and teaching., 1958 Apr-Dec (Box 31, Folder 58-22)
    - Correspondence with Schuyler, Professor R. L. of Columbia University about teaching versus research, the history of Columbia, N.M. Butler and Dewey, John., 1958 Jan-Oct (Box 31, Folder 58-23)
    - Correspondence with Wright, President Benjamin F. of Smith College about teaching versus research The Harvard Report, Conant, J.B., and Hutchins, Robert Maynard., 1958 Sep-Nov (Box 31, Folder 58-24)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence with Williamson, E.G., about WHC professional notes system, student personnel writings, a proposed series of lectures at the University of Minnesota on student personnel services and a discussion of the intelligence and academic performance of engineers., 1957 Apr-1958 Dec (Box 31, Folder 58-25)
    - Correspondence with Loftis, Professor J., of the Stanford English Department about a petition to increase the salaries of Stanford professors., 1957 Dec-1958 Feb (Box 31, Folder 58-26)
    - Correspondence with Handlin, Professor Oscar, of Harvard about important omissions of higher educational documents in The Harvard Guide to American History., 1957 Dec-1958 Jan (Box 31, Folder 58-27)
    - Correspondence with Berelson, Bernard, about his study of graduate education in America., 1957 Jul-1958 Jan (Box 31, Folder 58-28)
    - Correspondence with Pace, C. Robert, about his study of college and university characteristics, teaching, college environments and the quality of education., 1957 Dec-1958 May (Box 31, Folder 58-29)
    - Correspondence with Plock, Richard H. of the Association of Governing Boards, about academic government., 1956 Sep-1958 Sep (Box 31, Folder 58-30)
    - Correspondence with an architect on the staff of Pereira & Luckman about the design for the University of California at Irvine., 1958 Jan (Box 31, Folder 58-31)
    - An Art of Thought Exists, outline of WHC address on creativity at San Lorenzo School District Teachers Institute, San Lorenzo, CA. Folder includes correspondence and news clippings., 1958 Nov-1959 Jan (Box 31, Folder 59-1)
    - Chambers, M.M., correspondence about academic corporations, academic govt., WHC's University of Illinois lectures and Chambers' publication, The Grapevine., 1958 Nov-1959 Sep (Box 31, Folder 59-2)
    - Correspondence with Fullen, Jack B., about his effort to break up the Big Ten Rose Bowl Pact., 1958 Dec-1959 Sep (Box 31, Folder 59-3)
    - WHC memo to Henry, President David D., of Illinois about the education of administrators., 1959 Jan-Mar (Box 31, Folder 59-4)
    - Minutes of the University of Illinois' Second President's Faculty Conference where WHC gave talk., 1959 Mar 13-15 (Box 31, Folder 59-5)
    - Correspondence about WHC talks for the Richmond Area University Center, Visiting Scholar Program., 1957 Dec-1959 Apr (Box 31, Folder 59-6)
    - Correspondence about invitation from Coladarci, Professor Arthur P., for WHC to spend 1959-1960 in Japan., 1959 Feb-Mar (Box 31, Folder 59-7)
    - Correspondence about WHC consultation for student service programs at Southern Illinois University., 1959 Jan-Apr (Box 31, Folder 59-8)
    - Correspondence with Albertson, Jim, and Emens President Jack, about consultation at Ball State Teachers College., 1959 Apr-Jun (Box 31, Folder 59-9)
    - Correspondence with Hannah, H.W., about WHC consultation with the University of Illinois Senate Committee on General Education., 1959 Mar-May (Box 31, Folder 59-10)
    - 1959 Plus and Minus Thirty-Five, WHC commencement address at the Oregon College of Education. 11 pages. Includes correspondence., 1959 Nov-1959 June (Box 31, Folder 59-11)
    - WHC address at the Stanford Graduate School of Business seminar for Business Administrators of privately supported Japanese universities. 16 pages., published in University Administration in Practice, Nielson, Oswald editor, pages 3-17. Includes related correspondence See also 57-13 and 58-1C., 1959 Feb-Oct (Box 31, Folder 59-12)
    - Critical analysis of Corson, John J’s text on academic government, and related topics in higher education., 1958 Sep-1960 Mar (Box 31, Folder 59-13)
    - WHC notes for a talk at the Stanford Workshop on Administration in Student Personnel Work, "Student Personnel Work-Past, Present and Future." Also includes related correspondence., 1959 May (Box 32, Folder 59-14)
    - Correspondence with Gardner, John W. about speech Gardner needed help with, Howard, John B., of the Ford Foundation, and WHC’s work at Stanford., 1959 Aug-Oct (Box 32, Folder 59-15)
    - Report on the SUSE Higher Education Program for the Self-Study Committee. Stanford, 9 pages., 1959 Sept 23 (Box 32, Folder 59-16)
    - Correspondence about and copy of three page editorial review written by WHC for the Harvard University Press of Ulich, Robert’s The Education of Nations., 1959 Sep-Dec (Box 32, Folder 59-17)
    - Correspondence about and copy of 2 page editorial by WHC for McGraw-Hill of Williamson, E.G.'s The Administration of Student Personnel Services., 1959 Sep-Dec (Box 32, Folder 59-18)
    - Correspondence with Williamson, E.G., and others about four talks given by WHC at the University of Minnesota on student personnel services. See also 59-20, 59-21, 59-38, 59-39., 1959 Feb-1961 Feb (Box 32, Folder 59-19)
    - The Rise of Clientele Services in American Higher Education, outline for WHC talk at the University of Minnesota, 13 pages., 1959 Oct 8 (Box 32, Folder 59-20)
    - The Functions and Purposes of Clientele Services in American Colleges and Universities, outline of talk at the University of Minnesota, 9 pages., 1959 Oct 8 (Box 32, Folder 59-21)
    - Correspondence with and WHC memo to Maxwell, William Quentin about the course credit system, 15 pages., 1959 Oct-1960 May (Box 32, Folder 59-22)
    - Correspondence about WHC editorial review for McGraw Hill of a proposed manuscript, "An Introduction to Higher Education in the USA," by Penrose, William O., 1959 Sep-Dec (Box 32, Folder 59-23)
    - Correspondence with and notes from phone conversations with Odell, Bill, SUSE colleague about his Kellogg Foundation proposal., 1959 Dec (Box 32, Folder 59-24)
    - Correspondence with McGrath, Earl J. about the history of the college curriculum, the origin of normal schools and teacher colleges, and the training of teachers., 1959 Jan-1960 Jan (Box 32, Folder 59-25)
    - "Two and a Half Centuries of Institutional Research in American Higher Education," WHC paper read at the Institute on Institutional Research, Stanford. Published by the Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education in College Self-Study, 1960, 16 pages. Folder includes related correspondence., 1958 Sep-1960 Sep (Box 32, Folder 59-26)
    - Correspondence with Stanford staff, chiefly Hefferlin, J.B. during WHC’s semester teaching at the University of Illinois., 1959 Feb-Jun (Box 32, Folder 59-27)
    - An Overview of American Higher Education, lecture outlines from course of same title, University of Illinois revision. 37 pages., Spring 1959 (Box 32, Folder 59-28)
    - Correspondence with Kimpton, President Larry of the University of Chicago and outline of WHC talk to the University of Chicago Board of Trustees., 1959 Sep-Nov (Box 32, Folder 59-29)
    - Annotated Bibliography on the Government of Higher Education, prepared by the staff of SUSE. 80 pages. Includes related correspondence with Johns, Robert., 1959 Aug-Nov (Box 32, Folder 59-30)
    - WHC memo to Johns, Robert, on the coordination of state colleges and universities, Stanford. 7 pages., 1959 Sep 19 (Box 32, Folder 59-31)
    - Two WHC memos to Howard, John B. about the Ford Foundation Committee on the University and World Affairs. File also contains correspondence with Howard, J.B. and WHC notes of phone conversations with him., 1959 Sep-Nov (Box 32, Folder 59-32)
    - Selected Bibliography of Publications American Higher Education," prepared by the Publications Committee on Materials to Explain American Higher Education Abroad, WHC chairman, Washington: American Council on Education. See also 59-33A and 59-33B., 1959 Nov 25 (Box 32, Folder 59-33)
    - Correspondence, minutes of meetings, rough drafts of 59-33., 1959 May-Dec (Box 32, Folder 59-33A)
    - Report on the activities of the Commission on Education and International Affairs of the American Council on Education., 1958 Jan-1960 Dec (Box 32, Folder 59-33B)
    - Correspondence with Glover, Fred, and Edwards, Paul about readings on academic government for the Stanford Board of Trustees' bookshelf., 1959 (Box 33, Folder 59-34)
    - Readings for the Stanford Trustees, See also 59-34., 1959 Jan (Box 33, Folder 59-34B)
    - "Understanding the Academic World," WHC talk to the Cleveland Engineering Conference, Journal of Engineering Education. Pages 86-92., 1960 Nov (Box 33, Folder 59-35)
    - Six WHC lectures on academic government, University of Illinois. Includes rough drafts. See also 59-20 and 59-21., 1959 (Box 33, Folder 59-36)
    - Professional notes accession sheets., 1959 (Box 33, Folder 59-37)
    - Papers relating to WHC's consulting services to the Ford Foundation Committee on International Education, Howard, John B., Chief of Staff., 1960 Jan-Oct (Box 33, Folder 59-38)
    - "Conflicts in American Higher Education Affecting Clientele Service," WHC article, University of Minnesota. See also 59-19 and 59-20. MISSING., 1959 Oct (Box 33, Folder 59-39)
    - "The Rise and Development of Vocational Counseling," transcript of WHC speech, University of Minnesota, 21 pages. See also 59-19 and 59-20., 1959 Sept-1960 Nov (Box 33, Folder 59-40)
    - Correspondence with Morris, Michael, University of Nebraska Law Professor., 1959 Sep-1960 Nov (Box 33, Folder 59-41)
    - Stanford University School of Education questionnaire concerning WHC's teaching, Stanford, 5 pages., 1959 Jul (Box 33, Folder 59-42)
    - Correspondence with Johnshoy, Howard D., 1959 Sep (Box 33, Folder 59-43)
    - Correspondence with Osborn, Alex F. and Button, D.E., 1958 May-1960 Jan (Box 33, Folder 59-44)
    - Correspondence with Allen, Charles M., Dean of the University of Illinois., 1959 Jul-Aug (Box 33, Folder 59-45)
    - Correspondence with Sparling, Edward J. of Roosevelt University., 1959 Dec-1960 Mar (Box 33, Folder 59-46)
    - University of Illinois and Stanford students comments on WHC's teaching., 1959 (Box 33, Folder 59-47)
    - Correspondence with the University of Illinois Press about publishing WHC's lectures on academic government., 1959 May-Aug (Box 34, Folder 59-48)
    - Correspondence with Harvard University Press about WHC's academic government manuscript., 1959 Apr (Box 34, Folder 59-49)
    - Correspondence with Tead, Ordway, 1958 Nov-1959 Oct (Box 34, Folder 59-50)
    - "Governmental Aid to Private Enterprise," WHC memo to Howard, John B. of the Ford Foundation, 20 pages. Includes correspondence. (Box 34, Folder 60-1)
    - "The Liberal Arts Hoax," WHC address to the Faculty of the University of Hew Hampshire., 1959 Nov-1960 Jan (Box 34, Folder 60-2)
    - Correspondence with Distler, Theodore A., Laurie, James W., and others about WHC's participation in a panel discussion entitled, "The Validity of the Religious Tradition in Higher Education Today." Association of American Colleges 46th Annual Meeting, Boston, MA., 1960 Jan 12-14 (Box 34, Folder 60-3)
    - Correspondence with Eddy, Edward D. about WHC's and EDE's participation in the panel discussion above (60-3) and graduate education., 1959 Feb-1960 Mar (Box 34, Folder 60-3A)
    - "Cooperation Among American Colleges and Universities," WHC memo to Howard, John B. 28 pages. See also 59-38., 1960 Feb 26 (Box 34, Folder 60-4)
    - Correspondence and papers about WHC moderating Mt. Holyoke College panel discussion on higher education, Cubberley High School., 1960 Mar (Box 34, Folder 60-5)
    - Revision of 1956 version of an "Appraisal of American Higher Education.", 1960 (Box 34, Folder 60-6)
    - "On the Coordination of State Colleges and Universities," WHC memo to Johns, Robert reproduced for Gardner, John W. of the Carnegie Corporation, 9 pages. See also 59-31. (Box 34, Folder 60-7)
    - Correspondence with J.B. Conant., 1959 Feb-1961 Mar (Box 34, Folder 60-8)
    - Correspondence and outline about WHC's proposed American higher education documental history., 1960 Apr-Jun (Box 34, Folder 60-9)
    - Copies of WHC and Hefferline, JB's reviews of Shyrock, Richard H.'s The University of Pennsylvania Faculty: a Study in American Higher Education, The Annals of the American Academy for Political and Social Science., 1960 Apr (Box 34, Folder 60-10)
    - Papers related to WHC assistance to the University of Chicago Trustee Faculty Committee on the selection of a new chancellor., 1960 Apr-Sep (Box 34, Folder 60-11)
    - Correspondence with Quillen, Dean, about the SUSE higher education program., 1960 Jun (Box 34, Folder 60-12)
    - "Services Performed by American Colleges and Universities for Agriculture and Industry," WHC memo to Howard, John B., of the Ford Foundation, 25 pages. Includes correspondence with Law, Ernest M. of Boston University., 1960 Sept-1961 Apr (Box 34, Folder 60-13)
    - Correspondence with Hamilton College staff about WHC's Hamilton College correspondence., 1960 Jun (Box 34, Folder 60-14)
    - "Some Curricular Conflict," WHC paper read at Harvard University, 30 pages. See also 60-20. (Box 34, Folder 60-15)
    - "A Student of Higher Education Views Junior College Administration," WHC speech at the Western Conference on Junior College Administration, UCLA. Published in The Journal of Secondary Educational, pages 39-43. Folder includes related correspondence., 1960 Jan-Oct (Box 34, Folder 60-16)
    - Correspondence with Duke, K.E. of Stanford Research Institute., 1960 Jul-Sep (Box 34, Folder 60-17)
    - Correspondence with Dodds, Harold W., 1960 Jul (Box 34, Folder 60-18)
    - "Report to the Carnegie Corporation on the Activities of Cowley, W.H. facilitated by the Grants it has Made in Their Support," 47 pages., 1960 Aug (Box 34, Folder 60-19)
    - "Three Curricular Conflicts," WHC address at the Institute for College and University Administrators, Harvard University. Also published in Liberal Education, pages 467-483. File includes related correspondence. See also 60-15., 1960 Jun-1961 Jan (Box 34, Folder 60-20)
    - Correspondence with Riesman, David., 1960 Jul-1961 Jan (Box 35, Folder 60-21)
    - Outline of WHC talk to the administrative staff of Chico State College. File also contains related correspondence., 1960 Aug-Sep (Box 35, Folder 60-22)
    - "Prospectus of the Courses Taught by WHC," 40 pages., 1960 (Box 35, Folder 60-23)
    - "Write it Right and Brightly.", 1960 (Box 35, Folder 60-24)
    - "What does a College President Do?" WHC address at the inauguration of Miller, Harry K., Jr., Keystone Junior College, 22 pages., 1960 Oct 30 (Box 35, Folder 60-25)
    - "What Every Professor Should Know," text of WHC address to the Akron University Faculty, 32 pages. File includes correspondence., 1960 Oct 8 (Box 35, Folder 60-26)
    - Correspondence with McGraw-Hill about WHC editorial review of Political Process in Public Higher Education, by Kennan, Boyd R.. Includes correspondence with Keenan., 1960 Sep-1961 Jan (Box 35, Folder 60-27)
    - Correspondence about WHC consultation with President Sparling of Roosevelt University., 1960 May-Dec (Box 35, Folder 60-28)
    - Correspondence with Johns, Robert and others about WHC consultation with Johns and Miami University., 1960 Nov-1961 Jan (Box 35, Folder 60-29)
    - Correspondence with McGraw-Hill about publication of Professors Presidents, and Trustees, (WHC’s academic government manuscript), and "A Short History of American Higher Education.", 1960 Aug-1962 Aug (Box 35, Folder 60-30)
    - Professional notes accession sheets., 1960 (Box 35, Folder 60-31)
    - Questionnaire which led to the formation of the G9.2 Society, an organization of WHC's former students., 1960 Jan (Box 35, Folder 60-32)
    - Papers relating to the appointment and activities of the five-member committee on the future of the higher educational program at Stanford., 1960 Oct-1961 Apr (Box 35, Folder 60-33)
    - Correspondence with Chambers, M.M., about his teaching topics., 1960 jan-1961 Nov (Box 35, Folder 60-34)
    - Four drafts of opening chapter of WHC's "Short History of Higher Education" manuscript., 1960 (Box 35, Folder 60-35)
    - "The Core Characteristic of American Democracy (Political Pluralism)," topic 27 from WHC course, An Overview of Higher Education., 1960 (Box 35, Folder 60-36)
    - Correspondence with economists about WHC's memo "Governmental Financial Aid to Private Enterprises.", 1960 Jan-1961 Dec (Box 35, Folder 60-37)
    - Correspondence with Lorge, Irving about predicting career success of college and university graduates and other students., 1958-1960 (Box 35, Folder 60-38)
    - WHC notes from a discussion with Wert, R.J., about his negotiation of a $6000 grant to finance WHC's writing projects, from the Ford Foundation., 1960 Dec (Box 35, Folder 60-39)
    - Correspondence with McGrath, Earl J., 1960 Feb-Dec (Box 35, Folder 60-40)